<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of simonie and sacriledge preached at Pauls Crosse March 18: by Roger Fenton preacher of Graise Inne.</title>
            <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00668</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10801</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105579</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841306</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841306</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5881</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00668)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 794:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of simonie and sacriledge preached at Pauls Crosse March 18: by Roger Fenton preacher of Graise Inne.</title>
                  <author>Fenton, Roger, 1565-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Arnold Hatfield [for Felix Norton],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Simony --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sacrilege --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
         <change>
            <date>2022-02-20</date>
            <label>lb</label>Upload to github</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON <hi>of Simonie and Sacriledge,</hi> Preached at Pauls Croſſe <hi>March</hi> 18: By ROGER FENTON <hi>Preacher of</hi> Graiſe Inne.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Arnold Hatfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:2"/>
            <head>To the right <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Sir</hi> THOMAS EGERTON, knight, Lord <hi>Chauncelour of England</hi> my verie ſingular <hi>good Lord.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, I am inioyned, by that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend authority which in al duty I ſtand bound to obey, to publiſh
<pb facs="tcp:5881:3"/> theſe ſmall endeuors: which albeit they may paſſe inuiſibly vnregar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the meaneſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are ſo ſmall; yet the ſubiect requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the Patronage of the moſt honourable. Not that it is a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie (for amongſt wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I finde not mine ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie) but becauſe if actions interpret mens minds, the moſt part of the world be againſt me. Such is our conflict
<pb facs="tcp:5881:3"/> while we vſe the ſword of the ſpirit. Manie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects haue mooued and incouraged me to craue your Lordſhips Patronage. Your inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gritie, who I perſuade my ſoule may ſafelie waſh your handes of theſe ſpoiles. Your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable place and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, in whoſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er it is to cheriſh the tribe of <hi>Leui,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect a great part of our bodie. Your loue and
<pb facs="tcp:5881:4"/> affection extending it ſelfe to manie woorthie members of the ſame. My duty, your vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Chaplaine, who if I ſhould ſignifie to the world what incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments I haue receaued from your Honour, it might ſeeme in mee oſtentation, as if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued ſomwhat. Then let that fauorable coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance which hath e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhined vpon Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, vouchſafe the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance
<pb facs="tcp:5881:4"/> of a ſimple Scholars mite, for want of larger offrings. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this little teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of my greater de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, who ſhall neuer ceaſe to offer vp praiers vnto God for all ſuch bleſſings &amp; happineſſe vpon you, and your honourable family on earth, as may bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted fore-runners of your heauenly bliſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt bounden and dutifull Chaplaine, <hi>ROGER FENTON.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5881:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>PROV. 20. 25.</bibl>
               <q>It is a ſnare for a man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure that which is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and after the vowes to enquire.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Authour telleth mee in the fiue and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this booke the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth verſe, That <hi>A word ſpoken in his place, is like ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of golde with pictures of ſiluer.</hi> That is, as the outſide
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5881:6"/> is beautifull, ſo the inſide is far more precious, as gold excelleth ſiluer. So are the words of Wiſdome euerie where glorious: yet being fitted with time and place they haue an inward and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret operation farre more forcible and effectuall than otherwiſe they would, they be apples of golde with pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of ſiluer. Now as theſe ſiluer pictures, I mean the ornaments of ſpeech are not to be neglected (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in theſe honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble aſſemblies) ſo the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſubſtance which by a ſecret operation is directed to the heart &amp; conſcience
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5881:6"/> is euery where to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Wherefore when I gaue all diligence to ſpeake vnto you (right honorable &amp;c.) not onely things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for Chriſtians, but ſeaſonable for time and place, I was directed to this choiſe concerning the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation of things Hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, and the dangers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon enſuing. Towards the vnfolding whereof I am depriued of that vſuall helpe which other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures doe aforde: namely, that current of ſpeech and ſequel of argument where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by one ſentence followeth vpon an other in ſo good
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5881:7"/> conſequent, that the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and premiſſes of the place doe ſerue for a key to open our text. But theſe Prouerbs be certaine drops of diuine wiſdome (or gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den apples you may call them) each making an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire globe or ball within it ſelfe, whereof this is one. We may diuide it in the midſt.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 The one halfe compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him in the ſnare of deſtruction who ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God of his right in things hallowed.</item>
               <item>2 The ſecond, catcheth him who ſeeketh euaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to vnwinde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5881:7"/> out of thoſe vowes which are ſolemly made before vnto God: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the more he ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, the faſter he tieth himſelfe: for the firſt word is indifferently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied vnto both parts, and ſo make a double ſnare. <hi>Laqueus eſt deuora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſacrum; laqueus post vota inquirere.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>This kinde of ſanctified things intended by <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> is by conſent of all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitors taken to be of an inferior degree, whereunto we may deſcend by theſe few ſteps.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:5881:8"/> 1 That ſacred Maieſtie which is holineſſe it ſelfe in the abſtract, is then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned by man (as much as in him lieth) and iniured in the higheſt degree when it is blaſphemed. This is deſtruction in it ſelfe with God who raineth ſnares vpon ſuch for their porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and their arrowes ſhot againſt heauen fall backe vpon their owne pates.</p>
            <p>And it were to be wiſhed that this were alſo a ſnare of deſtruction amongſt men: for nature hath ſo preſcribed, and grauen it in the harts of men from the beginning, that blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:5881:8"/> is puniſhable by death. That curſed ſpeech of <hi>Iobs</hi> wife, <hi>Curſe God and die,</hi> 29. <hi>Iob,</hi> was grounded vpon a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon receiued <hi>Maxime</hi> in that time of nature, that a blaſphemer muſt not liue. And that Hethniſh king <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> had no ſooner acknowledged the true God, but made a decree, that whoſoeuer blaſphemed ſhould die a violent death.</p>
            <p>But admit there be no ſuch law eſtabliſhed: and that vpon this charitable ſuppoſition, that a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an common-weale will breed no ſuch monſters:
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5881:9"/> ſhall this be imputed for a want? Not vntill thoſe mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters appeare. For in the Common-weale of Iſrael there was no poſitiue lawe againſt blaſphemie: vntill ſuch time as a blaſphemer was diſcouered 24. <hi>Leuit.</hi> and than vpon that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the law was made. So if this wicked age wherein we liue ſhall bring foorth ſuch miſcreants and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable wretches, as ſhall dare to breath direct blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemie againſt the God of heauen, to the vtter deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and denying of him: then I take it to be a thing not vnworthie the higheſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:5881:9"/> conſultation, whether that <hi>iudiciall law</hi> of God be a patterne for vs in this kind. for if we adde to the law of God concerning <hi>Theft,</hi> for the better preſeruation of the publicke peace; let vs not diminiſh the law of the ſame God, for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of that ſacred name whereupon the publicke good both of Church and common-wealth doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend immediately. If there be a power eſtabliſhed <hi>de Haeretico comburendo,</hi> why not <hi>de Blaſphemo,</hi> much more? ſince the one ſinne is a partiall, the other a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall eclyps of Gods glory.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:5881:10"/> If the ciuill Magiſtrate doe carie a ſword and not in vaine: not a rod for corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction onely, but a ſword to puniſh with death: then let not that ſinne which by the generall conſent of all <hi>Diuines,</hi> is of all ſinnes ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely the greateſt, let not that eſcape the edge of this ſword. Thus much is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred vpon neceſſarie im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, that <hi>it is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the higheſt degree to profane Holineſſe it ſelfe.</hi> Yet this is not intended by the direct meaning of this text.</p>
            <p n="2">2 As God is holineſſe in himſelfe, ſo hath it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:5881:10"/> him to communicate the ſame vnto his Church: to make hir not onely a <hi>Catholike</hi> but a <hi>holy Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this end hath he ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified ſpecial meanes; that is, ſeparated them or ſet them a part from common vſe to effect holineſſe in the hearts of the people. Whereof there be three degrees.</p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> together with the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>Sacraments</hi> haue the firſt place, wherefore the <hi>Archminiſters</hi> of the Goſpell the 12. <hi>Apoſtles</hi> leauing all other buſineſſe, gaue themſelues to praier
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5881:11"/> and the adminiſtration of the word, 6. <hi>Act.</hi> 4. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour theſe is apparent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, for where theſe bee wanting the people muſt needs periſh. Yet ſuch is the malice and ſubtiltie of the ſerpent, that rather then this ſhall ſtand entire, hee will ſo worke as one ſhall deuour an other. The time was when <hi>Prayer</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing turned into a Maſſe, and the Maſſe into an idoll did ſwallow vp the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the <hi>word;</hi> the time is, when preaching hath well nigh ſwallowed vp Prayer, as if there were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing holy in the Church
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:5881:11"/> of Chriſt but a Sermon. Such is the peeuiſhneſſe of our corrupt nature, that where God hath combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſuch a louely paire of vertues together, we can not leane to the one but we muſt deſpiſe the other. Whereas in deed there is ſuch a ſweet concord and harmonie betweene them, that who ſo deſpiſeth the one, ſhall be depriued of the comfort of the other. They be the aſcending and deſcending <hi>Angels</hi> of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce betweene God and vs. The <hi>Word</hi> teacheth vs to know his trueth. <hi>Prayer</hi> teſtifieth that we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5881:12"/> his goodneſſe to be the onely fountaine of all our bleſſings. <hi>Preaching</hi> bringeth knowledge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which deuotion is blinde: <hi>Prayer</hi> exerciſeth deuotion, without which knowledge is lame and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable, the one ſoweth the ſeed, the other fetcheth a ſhower of graces from heauen to make it growe. By Preaching God doth ſerue vs with that heauenly <hi>Manna,</hi> the food of our ſoules; by Prayer we doe ſerue God which is the end of all our preaching. Be it farre from vs then to make a diuorce betweene theſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5881:12"/> two which can ſo well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That theſe ſacred means might take effect in working holineſſe in the Church of God, he hath ſanctified or ſet apart in the ſecond ranke, <hi>Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> for the miniſterie of the <hi>Worde, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> for <hi>Time,</hi> he hath ſelected the <hi>Saboth:</hi> for <hi>Place,</hi> the <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> for <hi>Perſons,</hi> the <hi>Clergie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 The <hi>Saboth</hi> ſanctified or ſet apart from common vſe to Gods ſeruice, is then deuoured when it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned by weekly buſineſſe, or lewd ſports, as about
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5881:13"/> this place it hath beene too much. But his roiall High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe whom God hath crowned ouer vs, no doubt to crowne vs with mercies and compaſſions, as hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it hath beene his maner in al his proceedings to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with religion: So hath he in his firſt proclamation cauſed the reformation of this point to be proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med.</p>
            <p>Pray we to God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinew and increaſe &amp; eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the reformation of thoſe things, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all controuerſie are to be reformed.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The <hi>Holineſſe</hi> of the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:5881:13"/> place is deuoured, when the temple of God is made an Exchange. <hi>Iohn.</hi> 2. 16. I meane not onely the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie place conſecrated to Gods worſhip is <hi>Holy,</hi> and therefore (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) not to be profaned by common imploiments, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 22. <hi>verſ. Haue yee not houſes to eate and drinke in, or deſpiſe yee the Church of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 Sanctified perſons ſet a part for the Miniſtery of the Goſpell are deuoured a thouſand waies: yea, rather then faile we our ſelues wil deuour our ſelues. That
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:5881:14"/> vnhappie faction amongſt vs about <hi>mynt</hi> and <hi>annice,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 1.</note> had brought ſuch a ſnare vpon this Church, as if Gods eſpeciall prouidence had not preſerued vs, the Papiſt on the one ſide, and the profane Atheiſt on the other, had deuoured both ſides with open mouth.</p>
            <p>Verily it is a ſnare to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour any thing that is ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified; but yet I am not come to the dint of my text.</p>
            <p>As the ſacred ordinance of God, the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments</hi> can not be mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred without conuenient time, place, and perſon, ſet
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:5881:14"/> a part for that purpoſe: ſo neither can place, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be fit for that Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie without conuenient maintenance.</p>
            <p>Wherefore God of his goodneſſe out of thoſe temporall bleſſings in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance beſtowed vpon the ſonnes of men, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed a portion for this purpoſe. Which portion is ſaid in my text to be ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, becauſe it is ſet a part from common vſe, to the maintenance of Gods ſeruice. For it is laid down for a principle in <hi>Leuit.</hi> 27. 28. <hi>Euerie thing ſeparate from common vſe is holie to</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:5881:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>the Lord.</hi> ſo that where the Scripture ſpeaketh of this porcion there to be ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and to be <hi>Holy,</hi> be <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyma,</hi> diuers termes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing one and the ſame thing.</p>
            <p>Theſe lie open to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured by couetous and needie perſons: theſe be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luring baits to intiſe a man to deuour them, but <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> giueth vs a <hi>Caueat,</hi> that vnder this baite there lieth a hooke to inſnare the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of the deuourer: ſo as he may ſwallow the bait and wound himſelfe: win the world and looſe his ſoule.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:5881:15"/>
            <p> Be it farre from me to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare the iudgement of the weake, or any waies to dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the trueth by Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or Leuiticall ſhadow. I know where I ſpeake, in the preſence of God and of thoſe who are able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcerne and iudge what I ſay.</p>
            <p>Giue me leaue (by your Honorable patience) to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten my ſelfe in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding of this text, ſo farre onely, as the Morall law of God which is perpetuall, and the euidence of his goſpel do ſecond the ſame.</p>
            <p>That precept of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to hir ſonne in the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:5881:16"/> third <hi>Chapter</hi> of this booke 9. <hi>verſ. Honor God with thy riches:</hi> albeit ſhe had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten it in the hearts of men by nature: yet ſhe had need to renew it, ſince many en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to blot it out: for it is a conceit co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, that for thoſe tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral bleſſings we poſſeſſe; if wee vſe them ſoberly without exceſſe, iuſtlie without oppreſſion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and charitably with ſome porcion relieue the poore: we are thereby diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged, as if no part ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were due vnto God, or did any wiſe appertaine to the firſt table.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:5881:16"/>
            <p> The <hi>Nicodemites</hi> were content to become Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians thus farre, that they would giue their harts vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt, ſo they might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe of their bodies as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſerued. Theſe goe a degree farther, they will worſhip God in ſoule and bodie both, that of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of the heart the mouth may ſpeake, the knee bow, the handes and eies be lifted vp, but for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring God in their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, they thinke it is more then needs, they will offer to God the oblations of their hearts, and calues of their lippes too; but not
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:5881:17"/> of their ſtalles. We will go with the wiſe men (ſaith <hi>Barnard)</hi> to ſeeke Chriſt from the Eaſt, yea we will fall downe and worſhip him: but we be grown too wiſe to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our treaſuries; that is, the renting of our hearts, we cannot endure to be tied unto it. If <hi>Paule</hi> therefore will make <hi>Agrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa</hi> a Chriſtian, he muſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept theſe bands too. But God will not releaſe vs.</p>
            <p>For as God is the owner and giuer of all, ſo he will be acknowledged by * a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacrum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aluin. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eb.</hi> 1. 4</note> rent to be Lord of all. He gaue bleſſings to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Abraham</hi> repaid part
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:5881:17"/> in acknowledgement of that gift, 14. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> The land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was giuen vnto his poſteritie, but that ſacred tribute was reſerued as holy to the Lord. For want of the paime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wherof God doth often deſtraine, and reenter vpon his own: reſtraining the influence of the heauen and ſap of the earth, as 3. <hi>Mal.</hi> 10. <hi>Bring the tithe, and ſee if I will not open the windowes of heauen, &amp;c.</hi> Therefore the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen were ſhut before, becauſe this dutie was kept backe. <hi>Si Domino decimam non dederis, tu ad de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimam</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Serm. de temp.</hi> 219.</note> 
               <hi>reuoceris,</hi> (ſaith Saint
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:5881:18"/> 
               <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> when the tenth is denied to God, he reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth 9. parts, &amp; leaueth vs the tenth, as in manie fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines he hath done; for the quantitie which portion is due, I auer not preciſely, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue not proued it. Onely thus much ariſeth without queſtion. That as God is the giuer of all our wealth, and he onely who bleſſeth the workes of our hands: ſo in acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his vniuerſall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, he will haue a part thereof ſet a part for his honor and worſhip.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly I hope, yee wil not determine any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:5881:18"/> portion for God, as if it were decent for vs to dwell in houſes of <hi>Cedar,</hi> and the arke of God to be wrapt in goats haire, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. Or to honor God as wee honor the poore, with ſome colde beneuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. If any be of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he is not farre from <hi>Ieroboams:</hi> for he made the baſe of the people the <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie;</hi> theſe make the <hi>Clergie</hi> the baſe and meaneſt of the people. Is this to giue to God that which is Gods, or to <hi>Honor</hi> him with our riches? But what tell wee you of God? you profeſſe to honor him with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:5881:19"/> all your hearts: but doth he eate buls fleſh or drinke the bloud of goats? doth hee dwel in temples made with hands, or feed of the fruite of the land? Not ſo, yet he hath right and intereſt in all, and hath taken into his owne poſſeſſion a part to diſpoſe of at his pleaſure, 27. <hi>Leu.</hi> 30. <hi>verſ.</hi> and when he hath ſet his marke vpon it, <hi>All this is mine,</hi> he after diſpoſeth of it. <hi>Num.</hi> 18. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I giue it to the children of Leui,</hi> for what? <hi>for their ſeruice in the tabernacle of the congregation, verſ.</hi> 21. to what end? <hi>to encourage them in the lawe of the Lord.</hi> 2.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:5881:19"/> 
               <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 4. What is al this to you? the <hi>Leuites</hi> are gon and their law is vaniſhed. It is true, yet this ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is in force ſtil ratified in the Church of Chriſt, by Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> 1. <hi>Corint.</hi> 9. 14. <hi>verſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>God hath ſo ordained, that they which preach the Goſpell ſhould liue of the Goſpell:</hi> that is to ſay, as that right which God then had in his portion he conferred vpon the Prieſts &amp; Leuites for their ſeruice at the altar: ſo God hath ordained that that right which he now hath in your wealth, that reaſonable portion now ſet a part for
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:5881:20"/> his worſhip, be it what it will be, is conferred vpon the <hi>Clergie,</hi> for their ſeruice in the Goſpell: <hi>Sic ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit Deus:</hi> and that vpon the ſame moral conſiderations as before.</p>
            <p>God is the owner and giuer of all we poſſeſſe ſtil, therfore vnleſſe with ſome portion wee acknowledge his ſupreme dominion, we ſhall not onely tranſgreſſe natures lawe; but in time forget whoſe tenants we are.</p>
            <p n="2">2 This God hath a <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> ſtill, who be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſet a part for a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent worſhip then that of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:5881:20"/> the Leuites, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 1.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Hee keepes the ſame loue and affection towards his <hi>Clergie</hi> ſtil, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 40. <hi>He that receaueth you recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth mee, and him that ſent mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 There is a ſeruice to be done in the tabernacle of the Congregation ſtill, and a more painfull ſeruice then that of the Leuites, they ſerued by turnes, wee continually labour in that which ſpendeth a more precious humour then the ſweat of our browes.</p>
            <p n="5">5 We haue need to be encouraged in the lawe of the Lord ſtill, and as great
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:5881:21"/> need as euer the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 31. 4. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that ordinance of God ſtandeth ſtil vpon the ſame grounds. That wee muſt liue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaketh) of that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is ſanctified by the temple. Or as he ſpeaks more emphatically of our times, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of that which is hallowed, or ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified by the goſpel it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>By this you ſee (right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable and worſhipfull:) Firſt, that the right and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Church liuings is <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Decima<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctigal. qui eas recipit in loco dei eſt ſubro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus ergo quod Mel chizadec, Abraham obtulit de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimas eo confeſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſt Hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ris gradu ſuprae ſe excellere. Caluin in Heb.</hi> 14.</note> originally in God, not in vs: which therefore is ſaid to be ſanctified in my text;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:5881:21"/> it holdes in <hi>Capite.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any ſhall deuoure it by alienation or ſacriledge, they ſtand anſwerable to God himſelfe, and not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, in that day when all Courts ſhall be iudged o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer againe.</p>
            <p>Secondly you ſee that this right and intereſt in Church liuings which we haue, we haue by grant fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, we receaue it imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately of him: ſo is it the free gift of god; not as he is the author of nature onely, <note place="margin">Finis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximus dat ſpeciem in mor.</note> for ſo are all other gifts; but as he is the author of grace. For to this end hath he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen it, that by our Minſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:5881:22"/> grace might be wroght in the hearts of the people. <hi>Deus qui dignatus est totum</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Tractat. de Beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine Cathol. Conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis.</note> 
               <hi>dare, decimam à nobis digna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur repetere, non ſibi ſed nobis ſine dubio profuturam.</hi> God vouchſafeth to giue vs all things in abundance. 2. He accepteth one portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> backe againe, in acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that we hold the reſt of him. 3. That portion he hath beſtowed againe in behoofe of our ſoules. So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (beloued) with a part of your temporall goods you honor God: that part he ſanctifieth &amp; returneth into your boſoms, for your ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall &amp; euerlaſting good.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:5881:22"/>
            <p> What iniurie is it then to God that his ſacred por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by alienation and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanation ſhould be deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? What indignitie is it to the goodneſſe of God, that this right wee haue in things ſanctified, deriued from God for his ſeruice, ſhould be bought &amp; ſolde. That that right which is the gift of God, the free gift of God, the gracious gift of God, giuen for the perpetuall maintenance of the Goſpell ſhould be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with mony. I doubt it doth taſte of the gall of bitternes, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 23. &amp; ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time incurreth that ſnare of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:5881:23"/> deſtruction there threate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. <hi>Pereat pecunia tua te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum:</hi> for euen that money doth ſeldome proſper.</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe to ſpoile God of his right, is to ſwallow our own bane: yet becauſe lucre doth blinde our eies, the danger of this deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is not conſpicuous. Wherefore <hi>Solomon</hi> doth here call it a ſnare. <hi>Laqueus eſt deuorare ſacrum.</hi> I would gladly know ſome reall and material difference betwixt <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his bargaine and ſome of ours; ſauing only that he delt plainly, &amp; we deuiſe ſhifts to inſnare our ſelues, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 19. <hi>Simon</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:5881:23"/> offered money, and ſaide; <hi>Giue me power that on whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer I lay my hands he may receaue the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We offer money &amp; ſay, Giue me or get me power, that on whom I lay my hands he may be ſanctified or ſet a part for the <hi>Word</hi> &amp; <hi>Sacraments.</hi> What diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betweene theſe two powers, ſauing that that was extraordinarie &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porary for that time, this is perpetuall and eſſentiall to the Church of Chriſt, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of more worth.</p>
            <p>It will be ſaid, <hi>Barnard</hi> ſpake like a foole in obiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <note place="margin">Declam. ſuper Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquimus omnia.</note> this to the <hi>Clergy,</hi> there
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:5881:24"/> was neuer money giuen nor offered for that ſacred power, but for ſome honor or commodity thereunto annexed. It is true. And ſhall we thinke that <hi>Simon Magus</hi> did offer his money for the holineſſe of that power which he then deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Or was it rather for that honor &amp; commoditie which he ſuppoſed were annexed? It was that honor hee ambitiouſly affected, that he might be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>v.</hi> 9. aſſuring himſelfe withal, that though he had offred very largely yet if he could beſtow ſuch viſible gifts of the ſpirit at his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:5881:24"/> pleaſure, he would make himſelfe hole againe in a ſhort time.</p>
            <p>Yet I make no doubt, but the ſin of <hi>Simon</hi> was <hi>Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</hi> And who liſt to open his eies and looke about him, ſhall find that <hi>Simonie</hi> is not a ſchoole terme, or word of arte, but a ſnare to intrap the conſciences of corrupt men.</p>
            <p>Aske a Patron who vſeth to marchandize his Benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: and he wil proteſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, that for that right of Church liuings, deriued vpon the <hi>Clergie,</hi> togither with their function, hee knoweth not what it mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:5881:25"/> neither doth hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend any indignity to God or holy things<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he dealeth onely for that which is va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>luable and money woorth. And I doe verily beleeue him, for heere is the ſnare.</p>
            <p>Neither do I thinke that <hi>Ananias</hi> or <hi>Saphira</hi> his wife did intend any iniury to the holy Ghoſt, in retaining part of what the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues had giuen. Onely they thought that a peece of money was as well ſaued as not.</p>
            <p>I verily perſwade my ſelfe that <hi>Gehezi</hi> ment no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to that ſacred power of clenſing the leproſie: but onely perceauing the libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:5881:25"/> diſpoſition of <hi>Naaman,</hi> he knew that two ſutes of apparel, &amp; a tale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or two of ſiluer, might be taken with as great thanks as left. The Scripture putteth vs out of doubt, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3. 8. that when the Iewes kept backe their tithes &amp; offrings, it was the furtheſt end of their thought to ſpoile God. Wherefore when God expoſtulateth with them: <hi>You haue ſpoiled me,</hi> they wondered, &amp; ſaid, <hi>Wherein haue we ſpoiled thee? In tithes and offerings</hi> (ſaith God.) We know we had beguiled certain fat Prieſts and Leuites, who haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough beſides: but we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:5881:26"/> dreamed of ſpoiling thee. Well (ſaith God) you haue ſpoiled me. <hi>Hinc ille laqueus.</hi> Sacriledge and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie be ſpiritual ſinnes &amp; ſenſuall men will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue them, ſo much of the firſt ſnare.</p>
            <p n="2">2 They who perſuade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues they can very cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly and ſmoothly winde themſelues out of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſnare, are taken in this ſecond. For hauing got a hint from ſome, that tithes are not due <hi>by diuine right,</hi> they reſolue their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on this maner. Albeit by the law of <hi>Moſes</hi> God did binde the people of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:5881:26"/> Iewes to the preciſe pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of tithes) which was alſo zealouſly vrged by the Prophets) yet in the time of the goſpel it is a thing more arbitrary &amp; indifferent. So long as they liue of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, and are partakers of the Altar, it is ſufficient. Well, liue they ſhall: a certeine pittance they ſhall haue, wherewithall they muſt be content, and there an end. For when <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> met vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>Tabor,</hi> the firſt two vaniſhed. <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> his law was very charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, whereby that tribe of <hi>Leui</hi> was growen too rich, <hi>Elias</hi> alſo was a hot vrger of
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:5881:27"/> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> law: but there came a cloud which caried away <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with their <hi>Ceremonials</hi> and <hi>Iudicials,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> was left alone, who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be poore enough, and ſo we minde to keepe him. Admit all this were true, yet the ſecond part of my text makes a ſufficient anſwer to theſe repliers. <hi>Poſt vota inquirere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our progenitors &amp; fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers being taught by Nature to honor God with their ſubſtance, directed by Gods law what proportion was fitteſt for that purpoſe; animated by the examples
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:5881:27"/> of the primitiue Church in their voluntarie oblations, did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate a certein por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their temporals by ſolemne vow vnto God, deliuering vp to him their title and right, from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues and their heires for euer. Annexing common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>apit. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ul. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 285.</note> ſome wordes of fearefull execration, that if any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to alien or take them away, that his account ſhuld be without fauour in the laſt day. If after theſe ſolemne vowes, any <hi>ſhal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,</hi> that is, ſhal deuiſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and ſhifts to alien or take away things vowed vnto God; to waſh or clip
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:5881:28"/> that ſacred tribute, which hath Gods marke vpon it, hee falleth ineuitably into <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſecond ſnare of deſtruction. <hi>Laqueus eſt poſt vota inquirere.</hi> For as <hi>Leui</hi> paid tithes in the loines of <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſo did wee vowe tithes and Church endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the loines of our forefathers. They for vs, and we in them, haue inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted God in that portion, whereby we ſtand eternal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uini iuris eſt, id nul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eſt. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>tit.</hi> 1.</note> bound neuer to claime intereſt therein againe.</p>
            <p>Albeit we had libertie before to vſe eccleſiaſticall liuings, as meere te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porals: yet after theſe vowes our
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:5881:28"/> caſe is the very ſame with that of <hi>Ananias, Act.</hi> 5. 2 who for keeping backe that which himſelfe had conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated to the Church, and colouring the ſame with a lie, was taken in this ſnare of deſtruction, fell downe at the Apoſtles feete, gaue vp the ghoſt. The ſame ſnare falling vpon his wife, for partaking with him in that counſell. 1. <hi>For inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring after the vowes were paſt.</hi> If you inquire a further ground of this aſſertion, let it be the <hi>rule</hi> of common <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Offerimus Deo quod Eccleſiae tradimus cap. carul. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>ca.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>84.</note> 
               <hi>equitie,</hi> that <hi>No man hauing paſſed his conſent and deed, may change it to the preiudice</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:5881:29"/> 
               <hi>of another.</hi> That which is giuen to the Church is paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ouer vnto God; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that ſhall take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, without the conſent of God whoſe it is, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth direct ſacriledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and dealeth worſe with God, then God will ſuffer any man to deale with vs: ſhal not this bring a ſnare vpon him? He that will be rich (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle) 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 9. Not he that would be rich with honeſt endeuours, but he that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolueth, <hi>He will be rich</hi> by hooke or crooke, thogh he ſpoile god himſelfe, <hi>ſhal fall into temptations &amp; ſnares &amp;</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:5881:29"/> 
               <hi>noiſome luſts which drown me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in deſtruction and perdition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Admit after the vowes it be none of ours by right which is giuen to God: yet let vs inquire if we can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters themſelues; to get or part away ſomwhat. <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenti non fit iniuria.</hi> Alas be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued, our conſent for the alienation of Eccleſiaſtical <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mentitur Ananias Deo quia Eccleſiae fucum fecerat Apostoli Homines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt ſed non priua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quum Deus illis vices ſuas nandaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at. Calui. tu ep.</hi> 5. 4.</note> things from that religious end to which they were gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is nothing, becauſe the right originally is in God, and not in vs. For the act of <hi>Ananias</hi> in paring his owne donation, was not done vnto men but vnto
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:5881:30"/> God, <hi>Act</hi> 5. 4. becauſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the donation, the right was not in men but in God, and therefore cannot be taken away without his conſent. Let me paralel this point with the like.</p>
            <p>Tell me, what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that after the knot of matrimonie is duely tied by conſent of their parents and friends, ratified by the Miniſter: what is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon (I ſay) that afterwardes the conſent of both the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, of all their friends, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conded by the Miniſter himſelfe, is not able to vnty the ſame knot? Your anſwer will be, becauſe mariage
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:5881:30"/> is not of the nature of a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill contract, where God himſelfe hath a hand. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom God hath ioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned let no man ſeparate without Gods co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee Church endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ciuill where God is a partie. That which God hath therefore receaued, let no man take away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his conſent.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If this will not ſerue their turnes, <hi>after the vowes</hi> men wil <hi>inquire</hi> yet further, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God did euer receiue them or no? for the ſiluer ſhrines of <hi>Diana</hi> were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giuen, becauſe neuer ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of God. It is true.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:5881:31"/> But extend not this limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too farre. That is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous. Firſt then let not vs ſit Iudges vpon the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of our forefathers, it is a ſnare after their vowes to <hi>inquire.</hi> 2. Admit their <note place="margin">2. King. 10. 29. 30.</note> purpoſes were ſtained with imperfection, ſhall that make their deed void? God forbid. What acte of man is without imperfection? that deuout zeale of <hi>Jehu</hi> was accepted notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his golden calues in <hi>Bethel.</hi> Looke to the other Paralel. How many excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions might be taken vnto marriages in theſe dayes? if we ſhould inquire after the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:5881:31"/> intents &amp; ſiniſter affections of the parties married, with other by-reſpects, which make them not ſo accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to God, as otherwiſe they would, yet doth the bond ſtand firme before God and man; for there is more vertue in the good of an act to confirme, than im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection can diſſolue; els <hi>Iacob</hi> had miſſed of his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Gen.</hi> 27.</p>
            <p n="4">4 If this will not do, men will <hi>inquire</hi> yet further after the vowes, if God will not in ſome caſes giue his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to part with his right. No doubt, he that is ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to conuert his own por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:5881:32"/> to benefit the Church in ſauing ſoules, will be as willing for our good to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe as hee euer was to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. But theſe caſes be rare, wherein it is not darke what God doth warrant. As in that other Paralel of matrimonie, there is a caſe wherein God granteth a diſmiſſion, <hi>Math.</hi> 19. 9. So there is a neceſſitie where <hi>Dauid</hi> may eate the ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, which otherwiſe is not lawfull but for the Prieſts. <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 4. But to make God ſpeake where he is ſilent, and to extort his conſent where hee is moſt vnwilling, this is a ſnare.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:5881:32"/> 5 If euery way our conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences be inſnared, the next inquirie muſt be, how wee ſhall bee deliuered. Admit we haue robbed or begui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Church: it is paſt, we are ſory for it. Will not God of his mercy break the ſnare, that our ſoules may eſcape in the day of the Lord? No doubt hee that was readie to breake the ſnare of death, will be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to breake this ſnare alſo. But vpon what condition? <hi>Ezekiel</hi> maketh a direct an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere 33. 15. <hi>If he returne from his ſin and do that which is right, to wit, if he reſtore the pledge, and giue againe that</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:5881:33"/> 
               <hi>which he hath robbed, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no iniquitie, he ſhall ſurely liue and not die.</hi> If he reſtore, may not theſe Ifs be diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed withall? No ſurely.</p>
            <p>That of <hi>S. Aug.</hi> is firmly grounded vpon the booke of God. <hi>Non remittitur pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum niſi reſtituatur ablatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> For as in <hi>Moſes</hi> law <hi>Num.</hi> 5. 7. they were bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the damage with the principall beſides the ram for the attonement, which was the ſhadow. So in the trueth of the Goſpell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the attonement made by Chriſt vpon the croſſe, reſtitution muſt bee made by vs. Chriſt hath ſatisfied
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:5881:33"/> the iuſtice of God for vs? which was not in our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do: but we muſt ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the church &amp; our owne conſciences, beſides the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement. We will amend and be ſory for that is paſt. Wil not that ſatisfie? True. But can we amend ſo long as we abide in the ſinne? As the taking of it from the Church doth begin, ſo the keeping of it doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinew the faulte. So long as the ſpoile is in thy houſe, the ſinne remaineth, when the act is paſt. <hi>Eſay</hi> 3. 14. and where the ſinne remaineth there is no amendement.</p>
            <p>For the act we are ſorie.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:5881:34"/> Be not deceaued, God is not mocked. Thou ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt not be ſory for taking of that which thou keepeſt volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily. <hi>Sine reſtitutione poeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia non agitur ſed fingitur,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine.</hi> Without reſtitution no repentance, without repentance no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, vnleſſe we caſt that downe at the apoſtles feet, which was got by ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, we are further from repentance then <hi>Iudas,</hi> who notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding paſſed out of this life in a double ſnare of ſoule and body.</p>
            <p>Vniuſt dealing is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous againſt whomſoeuer: but beware of <hi>Sacriledge.</hi>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:5881:34"/> 
               <hi>It is a fearefull thing to fal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of God.</hi> Thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney may periſh with thee: but to ſaue thy ſelfe togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with thy money it is impoſſible. A rich man can not paſſe the needels eie without a ſtraine, nor a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious perſon without detriment. It is a ſnare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie way to deuoure that which is ſanctified, &amp; after the vowes to inquire how to take that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God which is once giuen. It is a ſnare to inquire how to extort the conſent of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> to robbe God of his owne. A ſnare to inquire ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictly after the vowes,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:5881:35"/> what God did take, &amp; what was giuen to ſuperſtitious vſe. A ſnare to inquire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours and probabilities for Gods conſent where he is moſt ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. A ſnare after the ſin to inquire how by ſome ſleight repentance wee might ſaue our ſoules and our money too.</p>
            <p>It is a world to ſee what a worlde of <hi>Inquiries</hi> the ſubtiltie of the ſerpent hath ſuggeſted to inta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gle poore ſoules. We make <hi>quaeres</hi> &amp; put <hi>caſes,</hi> &amp; beat our brains &amp; all to inſnare a troubled conſcience againſt the day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>I proteſt vnto you (right
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:5881:35"/> honorable &amp; worſhipfull) I haue brought a doctrine vnto this place which is neither newe, nor to my knowledge controuerſall. I haue purpoſely contained my ſelfe within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of common and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued groundes, laying them open according to my poore skill. Wherefore in the name of God &amp; his Church, let me commend vnto you the exhortation of God himſelfe, <hi>Malac.</hi> 3. 10. <hi>v. Bring in all the tithes into the ſtorehouſe, that there may be meat in my houſe ſaith the Lord of Hoſtes, &amp; prooue me, if I will not open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:5881:36"/> 
               <hi>of heauen, and powre you out a bleſsing without meaſure.</hi> Bring al the tithes, that were a bootleſſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, bring ſome rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable proportion, and it ſhall bee eaſier for you in the day of iudgement. And ſeeing God would haue vs to prooue him, let vs trie him if he wil be as good as his word. Prooue him if he will not open the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of heauen, &amp; powre vs out a bleſſing without meaſure. Prooue him if he wil not proſper the 9. parts tenne times more then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Prooue him if hee will not ſend a learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterie
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:5881:36"/> into this land, ſuch as ſhall be able to ſtande in the gap againſt an aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie, when pregnant wits ſhall receaue encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the altar. Prooue him if wee honouring him in ſoule, and bodie, and goods, he will not honour vs with a floriſhing Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell to feede our ſoules with health and peace, to preſerue our bodies with wealth and proſperitie to our liues ende, ſo farre as ſhall further our ſoules and bodies to eternall life; Which God graunt vnto vs for his <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſake, <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ</hi> the righteous:
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:5881:37"/> to whom with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holie Ghoſt, three perſons, one eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, euerliuing, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wiſe God, be all glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, praiſe, power, and thankeſgiuing, now and for euer.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>For</hi> conſequent, <hi>read</hi> conſequen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>pa.</hi> 4. <hi>for</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>read</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>pag.</hi> 29.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5881:37"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
